<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on fodblog</title>
    <link>/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on fodblog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-ie</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Let a thousand public AI flowers BLOOM</title>
      <link>/posts/2023-03-27-more-fauxpen-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2023-03-27-more-fauxpen-ai/</guid>
      <description>In today&amp;rsquo;s edition of &amp;lsquo;I told ye so, so I did!&amp;rsquo; is this post about FauxpenAI pulling access to a model of theirs and, oh ooops, there goes the reproducibility of more than a hundred papers who use the model. Soz.
That is, a critical piece of research infrastructure is privatised and entirely at the whims of some like product strategist in a turtleneck and leggings e-scootering in to their SV office.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open AI? Yeah right! Jaysus folks we can do a lot better</title>
      <link>/posts/2023-03-26-fauxpen-ai-data-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2023-03-26-fauxpen-ai-data-issues/</guid>
      <description>OpenAI have probably sullied the word &amp;lsquo;open&amp;rsquo; now for good. As this Twitter thread shows they&amp;rsquo;re anything but. More like FauxpenAI amirite?? Imagine publishing a 94 page-ML paper and not even describe, let alone publish, your training data. Sad!
But it shows we need independent organisations who collect and give access to trustworthy training data. Which is of course no news to anyone familiar with the Open Data Institute&amp;rsquo;s great work on data institutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essay on Narin &amp; Portnoo by Louis J. Walsh, 1931</title>
      <link>/posts/2023-03-25-louis-j-narin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2023-03-25-louis-j-narin/</guid>
      <description>My great-grandfather was Louis J. Walsh. This article in the Dictionary of Irish Biography holds as much information as I know about him. He had a pretty active life. He was part of the early 20th-century Irish Republican movement, had a stint in Ballykinlar interment camp, wrote quite a bit of fiction and non-fiction and was even the first district judge appointed by the new Irish state.
My aunt recently sent me an essay he had published in The Derry Journal in 1931.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
