<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    
    <title>Fionntan&#39;s Website on the World Wide Web</title>
    <link>/tags/state/</link>
    <description>Recent content in state on Fionntan&#39;s Website on the World Wide Web</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-ie</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/state/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Q on models for the Bunga Boys</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-04-06-bunga-q/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-04-06-bunga-q/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/fionntan/fodblog/blob/main/static/images/DALL%C2%B7E%202023-04-06%2012.35.44%20-%20an%20impressionist%20painting%20of%20a%20multicolored%20head%20of%20Silvio%20Berlusconi%20with%20the%20word%20%22BONUS%22%20in%20the%20background%20.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;Photo of BungaCast&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bungacast.com&#34;&gt;Bungacast&lt;/a&gt; (formerly known as &amp;lsquo;Aufhebunga Bunga&amp;rsquo;) – &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;the global politics podcast at the end of the end of history&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. If you hate political theory blethering about &lt;em&gt;technofeudalism&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;degrowth communism&lt;/em&gt; then, by jesus, you&amp;rsquo;re sure gonna hate this! Works for me though (actually, I&amp;rsquo;ve a terrible memory for facts so I&amp;rsquo;m pretty useless at discussing current events - but I do like chin-stroking theorising and open questions like this pod provides - I&amp;rsquo;d love to be on-point and detailed focused but, alas, I have sieve-brain and thus listen to chin-strokers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had an &lt;a href=&#34;https://bungacast.com/2023/02/14/321-covid-dissensus-ft-toby-green-thomas-fazi/&#34;&gt;episode recently&lt;/a&gt; about covid and lockdowns. I don&amp;rsquo;t really agree with the guests&amp;rsquo; anti-lockdown bent (or know enough to disagree with the consensus is probably a better way of putting it). But it did make me think again about the power of models in state decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fair to say the covid models were the most powerful predictive models ever used. Entire countries locked down, opened, and closed down again based on what was predicted would happen through epidemiology models. Or, at least, the predictions based on the models were given as the key reasoning and justification for the lockdowns. Which, I&amp;rsquo;m not arguing against, but what I am saying is this is a huge amount of pressure to put on a lil&amp;rsquo; model!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-stakes models about society (e.g. covid, the economy, climate) needs lots of people like that &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rUHunfH0XbI&#34;&gt;they&amp;rsquo;re a a bunch of cowboys!&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; priest in Father Ted. Sceptically kickin&amp;rsquo; shite out of something to see if it breaks. They also need the translators – those who&amp;rsquo;ll dumb it down a notch to explain the mystical workings of these models so that the brain-dead-slob public can build up their own rough idea of what&amp;rsquo;s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Covid isn&amp;rsquo;t really my point here but take the models used for covid prediction in Ireland. These were formed by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucd.ie/research/covid19response/news/irishepidemiologicalmodellingadvisorygrouptonphet/&#34;&gt;Irish Epidemiological Modelling Advisory Group to NPHET&lt;/a&gt;. There &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.ie/en/publication/dc5711-irish-epidemiology-modelling-advisory-group-to-nphet-technical-notes/&#34;&gt;are a number of technical documents&lt;/a&gt; published on government websites which aim to give transparency to these models. Now, take a look at just one of these documents: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.ie/pdf/?file=https://assets.gov.ie/122667/8379f0cc-5be3-4c89-9a1e-3b7328ae03af.pdf#page=null&#34;&gt;A population-level SEIR model for COVID-19 scenarios&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself some questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you, a regular Joe or Josephine, know this science is accurate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you feel this 13-page Latex document is enough transparency and explanation for you to trust the validity of these models?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would you like in place to explain this better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What people and processes would you want to test the validity of this model?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much explanation is enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What mediums should the explanations be done through?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;https://theodi.org/article/sharing-models-for-covid-19-guidance-and-tools/&#34;&gt;researched well-published covid models&lt;/a&gt; as part of my time in the Open Data Institute (btw, spending all work day reading about covid science during the first summer of covid, grim!). If you scroll down to the &amp;ldquo;Sharing Covid-19 models: examples we like&amp;rdquo; part there&amp;rsquo;s some ones which are a damn site better published than Ireland&amp;rsquo;s attempt. In particular, I like Alison Hill&amp;rsquo;s lovely &lt;a href=&#34;https://alhill.shinyapps.io/COVID19seir/&#34;&gt;web-interactive model&lt;/a&gt;. Play with the dials, look at that covid fly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, lo&amp;rsquo; and behold, two years after I publish that, this article drops down one day: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thejournal.ie/nphet-covid-19-models-5746932-Apr2022/&#34;&gt;NPHET &amp;lsquo;did not communicate Covid-19 models as well as necessary&amp;rsquo; to Government, says Nolan&lt;/a&gt;. I really did feel like that &amp;ldquo;I told ya he was a chicken!&amp;rdquo; Chicken Boo guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nolan said they warned Government that opening up hospitality and household visits over Christmas would put the country “absolutely in the wrong place”.
&lt;br&gt;
“In fact we even said it in the letter,” he added.
&lt;br&gt;
“What did that teach us? It taught us that we weren’t, I wasn’t communicating the outputs of these models as well as was necessary to properly inform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bingo bango.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My lukewarm take is that even if they hired a decent web-developed and a couple of science communication researchers they could have knocked up a really nice informative site in a few months and it would have really really helped all this for not very much cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, enough about covid, back to the politics of all this. This sub-contracting of reasoning and decision making seems a big challenge for trust and legitimacy of government decision making. Particularly as state bodies move to bigger data collections and more complex modelling in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have the political knowledge to analyse this further. But I hoped the Bunga boys did. So I emailed them the following spiel. And hopefully there&amp;rsquo;s a discussion on the next mailbag episode. If so, I&amp;rsquo;ll post it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q to consider for Aufhebonus Bonus episode.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mainly, it&amp;rsquo;s about the likely future of state decision making through modelling.  Take three huge topics where predictive modelling is prevalent – covid, the economy and the climate. A lot of decision making in these domains seems to be &amp;ldquo;well we&amp;rsquo;d like to do X, but if we do X then ours models say Y will happen – so the only course of action is Z&amp;rdquo; (Z being lockdowns, austerity, some government over or under-reach). And because the general public don&amp;rsquo;t have the knowledge or skills or access we kind of have to accept the apparent recommendation of &amp;rsquo;the model&amp;rsquo; without much ability to cogently rebut or protest.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It seems models are the next step up again in to technocracy. It&amp;rsquo;s not just unaccountable technocrats, it&amp;rsquo;s technocrats relying on data experts who in turn rely on models. This process get even further out of reach as states roll-out extremely complex AI techniques for entirely automated decisions making – &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/aug/24/councils-scrapping-algorithms-benefit-welfare-decisions-concerns-bias&#34;&gt;the AI says you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t get welfare&lt;/a&gt;. So the elected politician doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand the advisor who doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand the data scientist who doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand the model but they all still obey its decisions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;But where to go from all this? Don&amp;rsquo;t use large amounts of data? Only use interpretable models? And whose interpretation anyway?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;p.s. I live in a very rainy place and really need weather forecasts, please don&amp;rsquo;t take them away from me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Thanks, it was nice getting this thought of my head since reading &lt;a href=&#34;https://basicbooks.uk/titles/erica-thompson/escape-from-model-land/9781529364873/&#34;&gt;Escape from Model Land&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let a thousand public AI flowers BLOOM</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-03-27-more-fauxpen-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-03-27-more-fauxpen-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s edition of &amp;lsquo;I told ye so, so I did!&amp;rsquo; is this &lt;a href=&#34;https://aisnakeoil.substack.com/p/openais-policies-hinder-reproducible&#34;&gt;post about FauxpenAI pulling access to a model of theirs&lt;/a&gt; and, oh ooops, there goes the reproducibility of more than a hundred papers who use the model. Soz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, a critical piece of research infrastructure is privatised and entirely at the whims of some like product strategist in a turtleneck and leggings e-scootering in to their SV office. &amp;ldquo;Oh my Dogecoin stock is down 10%, I better dopamine-fast and exponentially profit on our AI moat!&amp;rdquo; they probably say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, go read Sayash and Arvind as they are 100x smarter than moron me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post does mention open &lt;a href=&#34;https://bigscience.huggingface.co/blog/bloom&#34;&gt;large language model BLOOM&lt;/a&gt;, which is inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This is the culmination of a year of work involving over 1000 researchers from 70+ countries and 250+ institutions&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;training the BLOOM model on the Jean Zay supercomputer in the south of Paris, France thanks to a compute grant worth an estimated €3M from French research agencies CNRS and GENCI.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re talking millions of euro and one huge collaboration to create this language model. You could imagine say like a CERN of large models existing – kind of like some factory of factories – hugely expensive to build the big factory, but small and cheap to let other orgs to use the output and go off and run their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to create more of these? Sure listen, what do I know about industrial strategy. Get the Mariana Mazzucatos of this world on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But think of the opportunities for public and private orgs if we&amp;rsquo;re rolling out open and trustworthy AI models in health, energy, transport, etc. These can be continuously maintained and improved with the right funding, collaboration and governance if the state grows up and put on their AI big-boy pants(/big-girl skirt/big person trousers).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open AI? Yeah right! Jaysus folks we can do a lot better</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-03-26-fauxpen-ai-data-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-03-26-fauxpen-ai-data-issues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenAI have probably sullied the word &amp;lsquo;open&amp;rsquo; now for good. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/benmschmidt/status/1635692487258800128&#34;&gt;As this Twitter thread shows&lt;/a&gt; they&amp;rsquo;re anything but. More like FauxpenAI amirite?? Imagine publishing a 94 page-ML paper and not even &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt;, let alone publish, your training data. Sad!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it shows we need independent organisations who collect and give access to trustworthy training data. Which is of course no news to anyone familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theodi.org/article/what-do-we-mean-by-data-institutions/&#34;&gt;the Open Data Institute&amp;rsquo;s great work on data institutions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s go a step further here. There can (and should!) be AI institutions. Independent bodies with a public mandate that maintain and release not just data, but AI code, models and APIs. Then small organisations, public and private who don&amp;rsquo;t have the compute or tech skills, can build services on top, benefiting everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a semi-state body whose sole job was to make an Irish-language ChatGTP – (CaintTG4 😀??). And you could submit new data sources to it. Or raise git issues in the code. That&amp;rsquo;d be fairly cool in my book (&amp;ldquo;How to Make Cool and Good Public AI by Fionntán O&amp;rsquo;Donnell Esq.&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of just relying on big tech to drop these from the sky, perhaps we use our powerful collective resources to drive the direction of big AI models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essay on Narin &amp; Portnoo by Louis J. Walsh, 1931</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-03-25-louis-j-narin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-03-25-louis-j-narin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/fionntan/fodblog/blob/main/static/images/DALL%C2%B7E%202023-04-06%2009.50.50%20-%20a%20wistful%20painting%20of%20a%20well-dressed%20man%20in%20the%201910s%20standing%20on%20a%20beach%20in%20Donegal,%20Ireland%20.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;a wistful painting of a well-dressed man in the 1910s standing on a beach in Donegal, Ireland&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My great-grandfather was Louis J. Walsh. This &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dib.ie/biography/walsh-louis-joseph-a8885&#34;&gt;article in the &lt;em&gt;Dictionary of Irish Biography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; holds as much information as I know about him. He had a pretty active life. He was part of the early 20th-century Irish Republican movement, had a stint in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abercorn_Barracks#Internment_at_Ballykinlar&#34;&gt;Ballykinlar interment camp&lt;/a&gt;, wrote quite a bit of fiction and non-fiction and was even the first district judge appointed by the new Irish state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My aunt recently sent me an essay he had published in &lt;strong&gt;The Derry Journal&lt;/strong&gt; in 1931. She was browsing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://donegalnews.com/2020/08/new-book-chronicles-history-of-six-donegal-parishes/&#34;&gt;Donegal chronology book by Thomas J. Plunkett&lt;/a&gt; and saw it had a reference to this essay by Louis. She then searched  &lt;strong&gt;The Derry Journal&lt;/strong&gt; archives and pulled a scan of the paper. She kindly sent it on to me as she thought I might be interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sure was. It seemed a shame to have this nice essay locked away within a scan of a newspaper on some archives site. So I decided to type it all out and stick it up here on this blog. I’ve also added an image of the original newspaper page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing under the pen name &lt;strong&gt;Cormac MacAirt&lt;/strong&gt;, Louis praises the beauty of Narin and Portnoo, two neighbouring seaside townlands in Donegal.  He hopes to convince the paper’s readers that they should visit Narin and the surrounding lands on their summer holidays. He also adds some history of the area, telling the story of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dall%C3%A1n_Forgaill&#34;&gt;St. Dallán&lt;/a&gt; on the island on Inniskeel and his grisly end at the hand of some marauding pirates (the 600’s, wild times).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His way of writing here is pretty fun. He has this big flowery style with long, run-on sentences that you just don’t see anymore.  This is maybe as much Louis J. as it was the style of the time. James Joyce skewers this style, and maybe even Louis himself, as he name-checks Louis in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulysses_(novel)#Episode_13,_Nausicaa&#34;&gt;Chapter 13 of Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainly, I just enjoyed it on a personal level. Growing up, Narin was our main beach to go to on sunny days. And when I’m home I’d be down there often for a walk and a bit of sea air. Also, myself and my wife were lucky enough to have our wedding celebration just by the beach. Now we live close by. And, well, we couldn’t ask for a finer location. So, reading this, it’s very lovely to have a sense of hands across time and think fondly of same big wide strand of Narin that Louis looked out on nearly a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-derry-journal-wednesday-morning-may-6th-1931---page-8&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Derry Journal, Wednesday Morning, May 6th, 1931 - Page 8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-weekly-causerie&#34;&gt;OUR WEEKLY CAUSERIE.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-old-mans-musings&#34;&gt;AN OLD MAN’S MUSINGS.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;our-own-country&#34;&gt;OUR OWN COUNTRY.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is astonishing how little the mass of Irish people know about their own country. Not merely does the Munster man know naught of Ulster, and do Cork and Galway appear more remote to the Derry or Belfast man than do London and Liverpool and Glasgow, but there are amazingly large numbers of the fairly well-to-do travelling classes, who have no knowledge whatsoever of the adjoining county, and often none of even parts of their own county. If, for example, a census was made of Derry City people who had travelled fairly extensively, and yet had never been in South Derry—had never seen the “Three Spires” of Magherafelt or “Knockloughrim Plantin’ ” or feasted their eyes on that wonderful panorama of fair corn land and beauteous plain and lovely wood and cosy hamlet, that breaks on the delighted gaze of the traveller when he has climbed to the top of the mountain on the road from Dungiven to Maghera and sees stretched out for miles below him the lovely Valley of the Bann—the result would be surprising.  So the number of people in County Derry to whom Donegal, with all its wild beauty and varied interests, is an absolutely &lt;strong&gt;terra ignota&lt;/strong&gt; would be astonishing to a stranger, who knew nothing of Ireland’s unhappy history and did not understand how thoroughly alien systems of education had taught us to despise absolutely everything that belongs to ourselves and of which any normal race would be especially proud. But one need not go to County Derry to find people who know nothing of the real charms of Donegal. There are large numbers of reasonably prosperous people in Inishowen and in East Donegal, who never saw the blue waters of Mulroy Bay glinting in the sun, or Errigal doffing its cap of grey to bid good-morrow to the rising day, or the glory of a sunset behind Arranmore, or Slieve League towering in the grandeur and majesty over the Atlantic that breaks itself in desperation at its feet, or the romantic glory of Glenveigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;holiday-resorts&#34;&gt;HOLIDAY RESORTS.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, how very few people even in Donegal itself know anything about the number and the various attractions of Donegal’s sea-side and holiday resorts. I thought I knew the county very well, for example. Yet it was only last year that I visited Narin and Portnoo for the first time. But I found that district so attractive that I would like to urge the claims both of it and of the other Donegal watering places on the attention of those people who at this time of the year are wondering where the are going to spend their summer holidays. For the benefit of those who do not know the geography of the locality, I had better explain that Narin and Portnoo are practically one. The picturesque village of Portnoo, where there are a very excellent hotel, conducted by an enterprising and most efficient German gentleman, and Mr. M’Loone’s up-to-date and well-stocked store, is situate within a mile or so of the famous Narin Strand. The place is easily accessible. One can travel to it by the Donegal Railway, over one of the most beautiful railway routes in Ireland, through Glenfinn and past Lough Finn, to Glenties, and then by bus to Portnoo ; or if one wants to see a great deal of the southern end of County Donegal, passing through Barnesmore Gap, and along Donegal Bay to Killybegs, and thence over a picturesque mountain road to Ardara, he can bus right through from Foyle Street, Derry, to Narin and Portnoo on a very cheap ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;narin&#34;&gt;NARIN.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When some of the very ignorant people, whom we grow in great numbers, see a beautiful place like Narin for the first time, they exclaim : “If they had a place one-tenth part as nice as this across the water, they would make something of it!” They mean that they would build a picture house and a promenade and introduce  a lot of vulgar pierots and have all the English Sunday “dirties” on sale in it, at least by Monday morning, and erect a number of garish dancing halls, and destroy the charm and obscure the beauty of even Narin and Portnoo. Well thank God, Narin and Portnoo are not “across the water,” and their charm is likely to remain. Those who cannot live without cinemas or whose souls are so vulgar that they delights in pierots should certainly go to Blackpool or Portrush. But for one who glories in the beauty of God’s world, whose heart is made glad by seascape and mountain scenery, whose ears are attuned to the music of the spheres, and who seeks above all things on a holiday health and peace and comfort and change, Narin has very special attractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;scenic-beauty&#34;&gt;SCENIC BEAUTY.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scenic beauty of the place is wonderful. All around are the Donegal Highlands, and Narin is situate on a lovely bay that opens out into the broad Atlantic. No place could be more healthy or bracing. You have only to sit by an open window in one of the houses that front the sea, and breathe the life-giving ozone that blows in from the Seven Seas of the world ; and if you climb any of the hills that stand behind Narin your eyes are filled with scenes of almost ethereal beauty—mountain and moor and lake and island and inlet and ocean—and your lungs with that seems like the very breath of life. To sit on such a hill on a summer evening and watch the sun go down in a blaze of glory and sink into the red sea that stretches beyond Arranmore into the great unknown, fills the soul with such a sense of beauty that is hushed almost into silence and can only exclaim : “Lord! It is good to be here!”  There is along stretch of white strand at Narin, that seems to extend for miles, and from any part of which it is a joy to bathe. There is an excellent golf course, and—rare instance of the enterprise of the local people—several free bathing boxes on the strand, of which visitors can have the use at any time without charge. There is plenty of excellent accommodation in the hotels and boarding houses and there are some very fine furnished houses to let. The late Cardinal O’Donnell, when he was Bishop of Raphoe, used to spend his holidays practically every year in Narin ; and no man was a better judge or had a finer appreciation of natural beauty. There are all sorts of interesting walks and excursions to be made all over the district.
MEMORIES.
But the place has more than scenery or golf links to recommend it. It is rich in memories, and any person with any feeling for our great past could not fail to find a holiday there very delightful. There are some very interesting pre-Christian ruins and traditions and tracks in the neighbourhood. But in particular I would like to draw attention to the Island of Inniskeel, its ruins, and its associations. The island derives its name from the agnomen of St. Conal Caol, who was a near relative of St. Colmcille, and died about the year 596. His name is associated in the Irish Annals with the Oain Domnaigh, a law forbidding servile works on Sundays which the “Yellow Book of Lecan” says was brought to Ireland from Rome by St. Conal, who had got it when on a pilgrimage to the Eternal City. St. Conal had a very devoted friend, St. Dallan Forgail, who was the author of the famous “Amhra Column Cille.” This was a poem written in praise of St. Colm, and the first version of it was composed to commemorate the great saint’s success at the assembly of Drumceat. Dallan proceeded to read it at the break-up of that great convention ; but as we are told by Colgan the slight feeling of vain-glory which the eulogy inspired in the saint’s breast brought the demons in whirling crowds above Colm’s head to the astonishment of his disciple and companion, St. Baithen. The demons must have a lot of other jobs to attend to now-a-days or only saints are privileged to see them, because otherwise addresses and presentations to curates leaving for new missions, or civic welcomes to more highly placed ecclesiastics, would not be the very  pleasant functions which they usually are ! St. Colmcille, we are told, saw the terrible portent himself, and at the once stopped the recital. No entreaty would ever induce him to allow the publication of the poem of his lifetime ; but by dint of the poem in his lifetime ; but by dint of importunity Colm was induced to promise St. Dallan that if he survived he might then compose a poem about his life. We are told that an angel brought the new of St. Colm’s death to Dallan, who thereupon composed his panegyric, “Amhra Coluim Cille.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-same-grave&#34;&gt;THE SAME GRAVE.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Dallan was blind ; but we are told that when the “dan” in praise of St. Colmcille was completed his sight was miraculously restored to him. He also composed a panegyric in praise of his friend St. Conal whose monastery was in Inniskeel. Dallan had often been a visitor at the island sanctuary and so great was his attachment to his friend that he had often prayed God that they might share the same grave. The favour was granted him in this way. Once, when he was on Inniskeel, a band of pirates raided the monastery, plundered all they could lay hands on, and cutting off Dallan’s head cast it into the sea. The Abbot had managed to escape from their hands ; but when the robbers had departed and he had returned to his despoiled priory, he found the headless trunk of what had been Dallan’s body. Conal at once appealed to God, asking Him to reveal the whereabouts of the head of his martyred friend. His prayer was granted. The head was cast up by the waves, and we are told that when it was placed by reverent hands beside the body of the saint the parts re-united as if the pirate’s cutlass had never done its bloody work. St. Dallan’s boy was then buried beneath the church walls. This took place about the year 594, and before the century had closed St. Conal’s reminds were buried in the same grave. The sacred island has ever been a place of pilgrimage since, and down the long centuries many miracles have been claimed for the hallowed spot. Inniskeel can be reached be reached at low tide on foot across the sand from Narin, and people are constantly making the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;turas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the island. The feast of St. Conal is on the 20th May, and the feast of St. Dallan on the 29th January. There is little Irish in Narin, because it has been a planted district and the old race have only pushed back into it within the last hundred years. But to those who are interested in the national language, as nearly all educated people are nowadays, a holiday in the district will furnish ample opportunities of improving their command of the tongue of Conal and Dallan. For the Glenfinn people have always regarded it as their favourite watering place ; and there is no Irish in Donegal like the Glenfinn Irish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;portnoo&#34;&gt;PORTNOO.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Portnoo has been honoured by being praised in song by a former Bishop of Raphoe. The Most Rev. Dr. MacDevitt—in those simple, unsophisticated days of my youth, when even Bishops wrote books and verses—paid this graceful and tuneful tribute to a place that he loved passing well :—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A voyage dreary,&lt;br&gt;
And coasting weary,&lt;br&gt;
Bring me to anchor in sweet Portnoo&lt;br&gt;
Above that harbour&lt;br&gt;
There is an arbour&lt;br&gt;
From storm’s wild ardour&lt;br&gt;
A refuge true ;&lt;br&gt;
I love to rest there,&lt;br&gt;
With friendship blest there,&lt;br&gt;
With sorrows few.&lt;br&gt;
’Tis a beacon seeming,&lt;br&gt;
With heav’ns light gleaming,&lt;br&gt;
For ever beaming&lt;br&gt;
        Above Portnoo.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Here some great giant,&lt;br&gt;
A Fenian client,&lt;br&gt;
Made a bed to lie on’t.&lt;br&gt;
For Finn MacCoul,&lt;br&gt;
The giant pillow&lt;br&gt;
Above the billow&lt;br&gt;
Here stands still, O,&lt;br&gt;
’Tis wonderful.&lt;br&gt;
From this granite boulder,&lt;br&gt;
This huge upholder&lt;br&gt;
Of the giant’s shoulder,&lt;br&gt;
I love to view,&lt;br&gt;
With rapt devotion&lt;br&gt;
The endless ocean&lt;br&gt;
In endless motion&lt;br&gt;
        Beyond Portnoo.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Behold the Atlantic&lt;br&gt;
By winds made frantic!&lt;br&gt;
With strokes gigantic&lt;br&gt;
It beats the land.&lt;br&gt;
Behold them arching,&lt;br&gt;
Those waves ! then marching&lt;br&gt;
In deep lines charing&lt;br&gt;
On Narin strand.&lt;br&gt;
I look and listen,&lt;br&gt;
While they swell and glisten,&lt;br&gt;
And swell e’er hissing&lt;br&gt;
And roaring, too.&lt;br&gt;
With anger groaning,&lt;br&gt;
With hollow moaning,&lt;br&gt;
Rush they, foaming,&lt;br&gt;
        Beyond Portnoo.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In that isle holy,&lt;br&gt;
Where pilgrims slowly&lt;br&gt;
Do tread, and lowly,&lt;br&gt;
Do pray and kneel ;&lt;br&gt;
Their heads be telling,&lt;br&gt;
In that ruined dwelling,&lt;br&gt;
While waves are swelling&lt;br&gt;
Round Inniskeel ;&lt;br&gt;
These stones caressing,&lt;br&gt;
I pray a blessing.&lt;br&gt;
To the world’s distressing&lt;br&gt;
I big adieu.&lt;br&gt;
Nor skies that thunder,&lt;br&gt;
Seas raging under,&lt;br&gt;
Shall my cable sunder&lt;br&gt;
        From sweet Portnoo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good Bishop was not much of a poet ; but at any rate these simple lines give a very faithful picture of the beauties of Portnoo and Narin, and I trust that as many as possible of those who read this article will determine that the summer of 1931 shall not pass before they have seen these beauties for themselves and knelt in prayer within the ruined walls where Conal and Dallan once prayed, and where they sleep side by side in their hallowed grave.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
CORMAC MacAIRT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/fionntan/fodblog/blob/d2266253bcdb92e38d81f206f6ebaeed2f1a5cc0/static/images/louis_j_walsh_narin_article.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;Scan of page from Derry Journal&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/fionntan/fodblog/blob/e1830c4df02381907e1e17e7d2766c63ddffbfc1/static/docs/BL_0001123_19310506_107_0008.pdf?raw=true&#34;&gt;Download the hi-res scan of the page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“for she felt that she too could write poetry if she could only express herself like that poem that appealed to her so deeply that she had copied out of the newspaper she found one evening round the potherbs. &lt;em&gt;Art thou real, my ideal?&lt;/em&gt; it was called by Louis J Walsh, Magherafelt, and after there was something about &lt;em&gt;twilight, wilt thou ever?&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt; – Ulysses, James Joyce&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
